[SPEAKER_00]: We were discussing the other day about the middle way.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was between asceticism, you know, the two extremes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the middle way is the enduring of thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yeah, that's certainly the way to cultivate the middle way.
[SPEAKER_00]: The way to cultivate, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the sensuality, like, from the context of thoughts, from the point of view of thoughts and mental images that appear in people's minds, sensuality would be acting out of thoughts, immediately.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have a thought towards something, you just act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no reflection, there is no sense restraint, there is no consideration, more or less.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to... that kind of... that's pretty much what defines sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as the Buddha said, it's the man's thought, lust and desire in his thoughts, that makes his centrality be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the beautiful things in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the nature of thought is central thought, but it's also... it's paired with that just immediate acceptance of it, immediate delight in it, immediate welcoming of it, which means immediate acting towards whatever you're thinking of.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the opposite way would be
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, say, you see sensuality is a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what do you do then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you try to deny the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you see that, yes, when these thoughts of sensual desires arise in me, I act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what if I were to not have those thoughts?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you want to prevent them from arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's now more aligned with that self-mortification, the ignoble way of just self-torture.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it can... it cannot bear the result you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's ignoble.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it does not... it's not wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not that trying to resist thoughts is bad, but, see, denying thoughts requires you to resist thoughts, but it takes it even further now.
[SPEAKER_01]: It overshoots in the other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because one thing is you resisting the thoughts, means exactly that, allowing them to endure, but resisting you acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And another thing is now to... oh, I mustn't have these thoughts to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, that's you overreaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not up to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why either giving in to those thoughts or trying to deny them, you're equally ignorant.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're either bound with sensuality or self-mortification.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're bound with the same domain of bait, as the Buddha described.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bait that Mahārāja lays down for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you then not go into either of these extremes?
[SPEAKER_01]: And see, by the way, it's not really...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean...
[SPEAKER_01]: It can result in extremes, centrality and self-mortification.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in itself, it's relatively subtle in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like... You denying thoughts, it's not exactly extreme, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, it already partakes in the way of extreme self-mortification.
[SPEAKER_01]: Shares the same nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's rooted in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all the acts of self-mortification, they would come
[SPEAKER_01]: Later on, in someone's practice of such kind, would be all sharing the same principle in common.
[SPEAKER_01]: Denial of the arisen thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mustn't have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even the Buddha was the same initially, when he was trying to find a way out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's no end to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can always get more.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can always do more and do more.
[SPEAKER_01]: To the point when the Buddha said, well, what if I were to stop breathing?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, I will kill myself and I will not... so to not have thoughts, so to not have unwholesome states arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then he goes, well, actually, that's... that's not going to help, that's not going to work.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the reason I'm saying this is because people kind of tend to dismiss, oh yeah, self-mortification, asceticism, or extreme sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are extremes.
[SPEAKER_01]: As long as I don't commit to those extremes, I'm in the middle.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're already either accepting your thoughts or denying them, you're not in the middle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the middle way is the way that basically can discern the arisen thought, not act out of it and not try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, the mind already needs to have been developed sufficiently to be able to allow the thought to endure without jumping into the action on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sensory strain needs to be developed beforehand, virtue needs to be established, because that will prevent you, that will give you a certain space to not just automatically act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you're not denying those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a natural progression.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, you see sensuality as a problem, you want to deal with it, so what you do, you deny the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you deny things you shouldn't be denying.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by denying them, you're baited, you're hooked to that bait again.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the deer herd simile in the Majjhima Nikaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, look, they got caught by engaging in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: What if we stop and we run on top of a mountain and we don't eat, don't drink?
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you can't sustain that,
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the third one is the one that finds the middle way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, what if we don't eat around the bait?
[SPEAKER_01]: We don't eat the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we don't do that which baits us into dharmāra's domain, but we don't shun it either, because that would all equally make us visible to the hunter.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the beginning of that discernment, is being able to allow thoughts to endure without welcoming them, because thoughts arise on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you thinking you can deny them, already implies wrong view, whereby you think you are in charge of those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're responsible for their arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're responsible for their acceptance.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're responsible for delighting in them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're responsible for acting out of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you don't do these things and thoughts are still there, that's not on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the reason why people then still want to get rid of those thoughts, is because it's unpleasant to allow thoughts to endure without acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's easier to act towards sensuality and it's easier to act towards denial.
[SPEAKER_01]: The hardest thing is to allow it to endure and not act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it can endure for days.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're not acting out of it and it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole pressure, emotional charge, it's all there, but you're not acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's easier to just get angry, or get lustful, just say yes, or say no, or act, express yourself quickly, deal with it, whatever it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's easier.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, the only reason you're doing it, is because the endurance of the thought is first, and it's still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, doesn't matter how much you give in, try to deny it, you always do it on account of that which you're not in control of, that bothers you, which is endurance of the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, it's futile.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of your efforts to act... they come out of it, as a reaction to it, are futile.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you really want to deal with the painfulness of enduring thought, where you're not acting out of it, well, you need to allow it to endure and then understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: See it clearly, understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's why the way I said, there is no wisdom arising on account of sensual behavior, and there will be no wisdom arising on account of that self-mortification, asceticism behavior of just saying no to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: There will be no wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pushing away or denying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because you just lock into a direction, and that's your principle of action.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it arises, I just say yes, yes, yes, or now you go the other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever arises, I just say no, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you conflate that with the idea of purity and then you feel even extra superior on account of your great determination that you eat once a month or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody can do that about you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're so special.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize even the unwholesome states that you wanted to abandon, the conceit, ego, pride, get amplified and you haven't actually abandoned it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the endurance of the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever thought... whatever the thought is, whatever the state of mind is, you have to allow it to endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that means not act out of it and not try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean maintaining.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to keep it in.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's again... that's not... it's not up to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just ask yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: The state of mind you have now, whatever mood you're in,
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you create it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you have a... did you, like, press an internal button that produced it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's what... that's kind of what you would think.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the kind of... That's the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's the implication.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the people... the view behind it's kind of, oh, this is mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is exactly why it's like, oh, this is mine, so I engage with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or when you start seeing problem with that, this is mine, so I will deny it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact is that that's still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize, oh, I can't even deny this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the problem is not in those mental states or thoughts arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is in you acting out of it, either towards or against.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, you are affirming their grip over you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're trying to wiggle out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that would be the beginning of the Middle Way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly like what...
[SPEAKER_01]: In the suttas, grasping the signs of your mind, cittanimitta, what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Grasping the signs of your mind for what it is, the mind, for its nature, the way it has arisen, the way it endures.
[SPEAKER_01]: The reason why people cannot grasp the cittanimitta, a prerequisite for the right view, is because they either act or deny against their own mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the mind of sensuality, they're fully projected towards sensual action already.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, the mind of sensuality fully projected to a denial of the entire mind, of all... the root of the thoughts, not just this specific thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're either underdoing the restraint or overdoing the restraint, but you're not doing the restraint properly either way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you'll be watching your breath.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be watching your breath.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like some people, you know, doing this meditation, just watching their breath.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then a lustful thought comes up.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must get rid of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must watch my breath.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must watch my breath so that I don't have lustful thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if I just keep on watching my breath, watching my breath as hard as I can, then, whatever, eight hours a day, I don't have any lustful thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's like the deer herd that ran on top of a mountain.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not experiencing any temptation from the bait for a period of time.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're not growing wisdom in regard to overcoming the bait altogether, which means the food will have to run out.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you can't sustain meditating, breathing eight hours a day, watching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Something will have to pull you one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll get sick, you have to deal with things, and then you're back to where you were before.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no wisdom there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Creating, like, elevated ground for you to be on, in regard to all these things that were pulling you around.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lustful thought comes, and you don't have time to watch your bait, because there's stuff going on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the circumstances, the suitable environment that was helping you not engage with the bait, is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, your freedom from lustful thoughts was only circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now circumstances have changed, and you're back to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by the way, there is no problem if you have lustful thoughts while you're breathing and you choose to attend to the breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can do that, because it is a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Will I choose to attend this or choose to attend that?
[SPEAKER_01]: But the problem is when people choose to attend breath with the view of denying the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, I will attend my breath and allow this thought to endure in the background of my mind, because it has a reason on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't invite it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will allow it to endure as long as it wants.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not give my attention to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will attend to my breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not, I will attend to my breath, so this thought is gone, I'll go away with it, it doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, now you... ah, so you're actually engaged with it and your breath is actually secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because this is now your concern, that thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's like when the Mahārā comes in the circus and tries to tempt.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha can't chase him away.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't kick him and tell him, you know, get lost.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can just not provide him a basis to latch on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then Mahārā leaves you on his own.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, literally, thoughts of sensuality come and like flies fly around you, but they have nothing to land on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless you provide something suitable for them to land on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when even in the satsang says you don't pay attention to these thoughts, you don't do it at the expense of denying their presence, it's because they're present, you don't give them your attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: I wouldn't have to not give you my attention if you are not here.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, if I'm instructed to not give you my attention, means I know you are here.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for the duration of that endurance of your presence here, I will not give you my attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not, I will not give you my attention, I will not give you my attention, I hope he disappears.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's wishful thinking now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're actually still denying the presence of that thing that you had nothing to do with.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how Māra gets you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's still his domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Affirming or denying, it's his domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you say it's being economists?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that will be the outcome of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you cultivate this long enough, Māra will leave you alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pressure will not be able to overwhelm your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not if you cultivate sense restraint in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's necessary basis for you to see the middle way.
[SPEAKER_01]: For you to stop denying, trying to deny thoughts and states of mind, but allow them to endure and then basically you become stronger than those states of mind, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through having them endure and not acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not losing your sense restraint and not trying to deny it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you're cultivating the middle way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yes, you will become economist.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's imperturbable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what you've been cultivating.
[SPEAKER_00]: But those states will dissipate, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: There will be less pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, but that's a side effect, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your concern is that you not be moved by those states, even if they last forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the attitude that you should have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like I will deny these states forever after.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or I will indulge in these states forever after.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would be immovable in regard to these states.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha said, be like water, be like fire, be like... be like earth and wind that doesn't get affected by things that sort of come through.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't practice... like, I mean... if you want to make that an actual factual practice, yeah, you... that's done so on the level of the mental states.
[SPEAKER_01]: What mood am I in?
[SPEAKER_01]: How is that mood affecting my action?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I lashing out?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I binge eating?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I seeking centrality?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I irritable?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I angry?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I expressing it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I being perturbed by these states of mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Means I don't see the mind for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't see its nature for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am not grasping the sign of the mind correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind of a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, sign of the mind is a sign, oh, there is an enduring state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't invite it, but I'm certainly not delighting in it or accepting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing it for what it is, an enduring phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you start seeing that, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're already understanding mind to a greater degree.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if I start doing this with the idea that... oh, yeah, so that...
[SPEAKER_00]: Doing what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Watching my mind, so that I can get rid of... Well, you will inevitably start doing it in a wrong way as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's why the... reading the suttas, the... yeah, you have to start somewhere and then don't take your start at face value.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take it with a pinch of salt, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever you're doing, even if it makes sense, okay, let's see, let's test this.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a sense, let's reflect even more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's see how unperturbed I am when these things arise and so on, or if I think certain thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you'll see.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yeah, you will have to start somehow.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you do start,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're gonna be starting pretty much, like, on your own terms, as I often say, which is a wrong way to start.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have no other way than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you have to start somehow.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you recognize that, wait, it's not me contemplating this mind, seeing, oh, my mind is like this, and then I'm sticking to observation of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more like just finding the state of mind that's already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's already effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already proper satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm mindful of my mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am depressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm elated.
[SPEAKER_01]: My mind is lustful.
[SPEAKER_01]: My mind is angry.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start like that, but you want to remove yourself from that equation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you doing this observation?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, why are you even able to... Oh, my mind is lustful.
[SPEAKER_01]: My mind is angry.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why are you able to do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the mind is already that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You find it there, already, enduring as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, so whether I'm doing this or not doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: What really matters is just not lose that peripheral sight of the state of mind that's enduring, whether I look at it or not look at it, or try to outrun it, or delight in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah!
[SPEAKER_01]: It defines my whole experience as a whole, my whole behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to see it on that peripheral level, not on the level of I'm attending to my mind, which is kind of impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you've got a peaceful state of mind, this is the peace...
[SPEAKER_01]: Same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't be negligent in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't lose it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't distract yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't ignore it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now it's peaceful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Have I created that peace?
[SPEAKER_01]: Did I create that state of mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I know where it came from?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I know when it's... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's agreeable now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let me then not delight in agreeability of the state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when that agreeability changes, I will not be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, equally, when the state of mind that endures is disagreeable, you're not delighting in it, which means it's not affecting you as much, which means you don't need to be fretting over and, I must get rid of this, I must deal with this, because it's not affecting you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that was the only problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem wasn't that the state of mind arose one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is that you were affected by it and you were resisting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not being affected by whatever state of mind, not being affected... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then seeing that the state of mind are discerned on a peripheral level, not on the level of your attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm looking at my state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind is on the level of sense organs, not sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what people attend is sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm attending to sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the state of mind is what's peripheral to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have angry thoughts, means you can't have angry thoughts if the mind is not angry.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you recognize, okay, I have angry thoughts, which means the state of mind it endures is a state of anger, which is going to feel ambiguous initially, because people want to have things clear-cut where they can attend to, which is the result of an untrained mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But training the mind to the sight of the peripheral image of the mind is what developing citta-nimitta is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing the mind for what it is, without over-attending it, without under-attending it and forgetting about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you cannot see that, then you cannot endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not seeing that, means you're already not enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you are either resisting it or overly welcoming it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can't endure those thoughts, you can't endure the mind if you can't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you have a view that you shouldn't be enduring it, you will never see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, if you have a view that you should be denying those thoughts that represent the state of mind behind them, you will not be able to even endure it, because your view is to not endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must get rid of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if habitually you just have a state of mind that you immediately just act out of, again, you're not enduring it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're doing it because you can't endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, the first and foremost, even if you cannot attend
[SPEAKER_01]: Properly, in that peripheral manner, to your state of mind, the only way you would be able to do so, if you start enduring whatever emotional mood you're in, not get out of it, not try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, but sensuality is bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, it's very bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't act out of it, you don't welcome it, you don't delight in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean you go out and try to remove these thoughts that are there, because that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: That means you're engaging with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to basically be movable in regard to that which moves you, not get out and remove that which moves you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because how can you go out and move that which moves you without being moved, without moving yourself?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I want to be movable by removing, making effort to remove that which moves me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, then you're not immovable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you've been moved.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you have to go and move this away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which you're trying to get rid of.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only way to become immovable, imperturbable, as the Buddha would say in the suttas, is to then stop interfering with that which perturbs you and actually stop being perturbed by it, while it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're perturbed by it, by acting out of it, you're perturbed by it, by trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like when the Buddha said to Angulimala, he says, stop running, stop running.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, he said it to the Buddha, stop running.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, he said.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I stopped, I stopped moving, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you're the one that's running.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, you're the one that still moves.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, allowing thoughts, state of mind, to endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they're pleasant, endurance will be manifested by you not acting towards that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they're unpleasant, the endurance will be manifested by you not acting or trying to get rid of that displeasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you see, sense-restraint is already developing that principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you start acting beforehand, being sense-restrained and virtuous, and then you actually get to understand the principle behind it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which results, by understanding of it, will result in immovability.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that would have not been possible if there was no behavior of sense-restraint being performed beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wildness, running around.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what Middle Way is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The immovable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the complete immovability in the face of any phenomenon or state of mind that arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can't ask for more.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need more.